[Music]
[Applause]
greetings and salutations this is a Bob
Dole hottie with the bitter truth where
we may not have all the answers but
we're gonna ask an awful lot of
questions those of you that are not
already can become a bitter pill at
patreon.com forward slash the bitter
truth and as always you can get some
freshly toasted bumper stickers and
stuff like that we are celebrating one
year of the bitter truth so excuse me I
may be doubling up on rewards and stuff
like that I can't make a concrete
promise because I just kind of thought
of it so but today my guest is someone
that I've looked up to for quite a while
his name is John John Kiriakou if you've
not heard of him you should know who he
is he was a CIA analyst senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee on counterterrorism
he's been an expert on ABC News he's on
all the channels these days he's I've
seen him on RT Jimmy door everybody is
talking to this man he's one of the
first CIA anti-torture whistleblowers
that was jailed during the Obama
administration that's kind of key to
note and we're gonna talk about that
he's note a noted author he's written a
reluctant spy the convenient terrorists
the weird Wonderland of America's Secret
Wars
doing time like a spy taught to survive
in prison we talked about that a little
bit he's also a founding member of
veteran intelligent professionals of for
sanity and he's one of the founding
members along with Bill Binney if you
know who he is and John Kerry aku are
you there I am thanks for having me hey
thanks for coming on man I really am
appreciative that you came on so so I
know I know your times a little tight so
I'm going to kind of just jump into some
stuff initially obviously when when you
came forward with the CIA torture of
prisoners that was under the Bush
administration correct yeah the torture
took place under the Bush administration
between 2002 and 2005 that we know of
it may have dragged on longer but
certainly the administration never
admitted to it right and then and then
and obviously you are already working in
that arena correct yeah I joined the CIA
in January of 1990 rose up through the
ranks
ended up as chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after the 9/11 attacks I was the
executive assistant to the CIA's deputy
director and and I left the CIA in
mid-2014 waiting for someone expecting
someone to say something about the
torture program which I believed was so
patently illegal
besides being immoral and unethical I I
thought for sure somebody would say
something and they never did and I
waited for three and a half more years
and then finally I did and what what
method did you take with that was it the
some of the things that we've seen
before for example like with that
Snowden or with Chelsea Manning where
you were able to get information out and
then get it into the hands of of a
reporter or how did that come about yes
and no or maybe I should more accurately
say no and yes I didn't take anything
out I I knew that I would be accused of
theft of government property which is a
felony and falls under the Espionage Act
if I had done that and I decided not to
what I did is I talked to Brian Ross of
ABC News he's the he's a multiple Emmy
winning investigative journalist and I
agreed to sit for an interview and I
said three things in that interview I
said that the CIA was torturing its
prisoners I said that torture was
official US government policy it was not
the result of a rogue officer which is
what President Bush had said and I said
finally that the policy had been
personally approved by the president
which he had always denied up until then
right right and then um and then explain
how you got in the hot water yeah yeah
well did you allow sorry sorry no you
did you think you were kind of in the
clear before the Obama administration
and how did that kind of process begin
yeah in fact I knew for for certain that
I was in the clear the FBI as you might
imagine started investigating me the day
after that
interview that was December of 2007 they
investigated me for a full year until
December of 2008 and then in December of
2008 they sent my attorneys something
called a declination letter where they
said that they had completed their
investigation and they were declining to
prosecute me they said that I hadn't
committed a crime that the torture
program was was generally known in
Washington I had just confirmed the
information rather than leaked the
information so they closed the case
three weeks later Barack Obama becomes
president and my old nemesis John
Brennan becomes the deputy national
security adviser he then secretly asked
the Justice Department to reopen the
case against me which they did I had no
idea that this case which had just been
closed three weeks earlier was now
reopened and for the next three years
the FBI tapped my phones they
intercepted my emails and they had three
teams of FBI agents following me
everywhere I went I was working on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee at
the time right so it's not like I was
involved in you know some kind of
subterfuge or anything right but they
they investigated me for the next three
years I'll jump ahead and tell you that
in discovery which we received after I
was arrested in January of 2012 we found
a memo from John Brennan to Eric Holder
saying charge him with espionage and
Eric Holder responded my people don't
think he committed espionage and then
Brennan wrote back and said charge him
anyway and make him defend himself which
is what they did they charged me with
three counts of espionage one count of
violating the intelligence identities
Protection Act of 1981 and one count of
making a false statement I hadn't
committed espionage I hadn't made any
false statement and I did confirm the
name of a former colleague to to a
journalist but the name was never made
public right but that's what they that's
what they hung their hats on you know at
first I was looking at 45 years Jesus
and and I refused to take a plea for a
full year and they kept coming down in
their offers my lead attorney told me
that he had been an attorney in
Washington for 50 years and he had never
seen a justice department come down in
their offers of time and I said well why
are they doing that and he said because
they have no case and they know they
have no case so they waited until I went
bankrupt and then they dropped four of
the five charges but that's what they do
you know they overcharged it's called
charge stacking and they wait until
you're bankrupt and then they say okay
you take a plea for 30 months you do 23
months or we go to trial and nobody ever
wins a trial and you're looking
realistically at 18 to 24 years and my
lawyers said it'll cost you another 3
million for us to defend you so you know
what do you do comes an economic
decision right well it was it the thing
is the the accusation of making false
statements it's been proven that there
was an enhanced interrogation program so
on what grounds did they say you were
making false statements you know that's
a great question and it's something that
journalists never asked me in August of
2012 I remember sitting in the
conference room at Akin Gump & Straus
one of the most important law firms in
the world right they have they have
something like 14 thousand lawyers all
over the world and one of the lawyers
the one that I that I liked and trusted
the most said you know we've been
spending so much time on these on these
espionage charges we've never even
discussed the false statements charge he
said what exactly is the false statement
supposed to have been and everybody
looked at me and I said I'm not really
sure it had something to do with my
first book when I when I sent my first
book in for clearance I had written to a
friend of mine I sent the book in for
clay
and I laid it on thick I said and they
interpreted that to mean that I had lied
in order to get the book cleared hmm but
I never lied to get the book cleared
right I mean the in fact they didn't
clear the book they chopped out 90 pages
so nothing no classified information was
ever revealed in the book I actually
went by the book and and I followed the
rules right and they ended up they
couldn't defend that charge anyway so
they just they just withdrew it Wow it's
crazy but the thing is I still spent you
know a hundred two hundred thousand
dollars defending myself just against
that one charge right right and what
makes me so angry to hear your story and
I've seen you interviewed before and the
the the the one thing that always just
really chaps my ass is that this was
supposed to be under the most
transparent administration that was the
promise you know oh
listen that's the whole that's the whole
crux of this story
now you're gonna you're gonna make me do
my spiel here I see a naja acted my
blood still boils when I think about
this you know Act was written in 1917
yes
to combat German saboteurs during the
First World War it doesn't even mention
classified the words classified
information because the classification
system wasn't even invented until the
1950s right right and and the law was
never even updated until the 1990s and
even then the update was only technical
in nature right so between 1917 and the
inauguration of Barack Obama three
Americans were charged with espionage
for speaking to the media just in the
eight years that Obama was president he
charged eight people with espionage for
speaking to the media hmm he was not the
most transparent president in history
he was quite truthfully the least
transparent president history he was the
enemy of transparency yep he was the
enemy certainly of whistleblowers oh
well eventually national security
whistleblowers well he's the buddy of
his donors I mean the one thing I hate
about the Espionage Act is it does not
allow for the public good you know when
you're trying okay when you're trying a
case intent is you know nine
if you're in a bar and you intentionally
walk up somebody with a bottle and hit
him in the head and that was a plan
that's first-degree murder if that's
right if the death was the result of a
fight and it was a crime of passion then
that's a second-degree murder so intent
is everything and so the the challenge
I've always had the Espionage Act it
does not allow for the public good you
know they'll they'll put you or Chelsea
Manning or Ed Snowden into this category
of other spies we'll wait a minute wait
what was their intent the intent was the
shady this is a very important point
that you raised there is no affirmative
defense in an espionage Act case I've
spoken a number of times with Ed Snowden
about this he wants to come home and
he's willing to go on trial and I urge
him in every conversation not to do it
right he says he's willing to go to
prison if he can stand up in the
courtroom and he can say why he did what
he did and I said and they will never
let you say why you did what you did no
there's no affirmative a defense to the
Espionage Act you're not going to be
allowed to say a single word in the
courtroom no and and and they do that on
purpose sure you know they could easily
pass an amendment saying okay well if
somebody leaks information that is in
the public good you're you're exposing
evidence of waste fraud abuse illegality
or threats to the public health or
public safety which is the definition of
whistleblowing the legal definition then
you should be allowed to to go forward
with that and you're not you're not
allowed to do that Wow see any what's
amazing to me is like and and and you
know Ed Snowden I do not admire him from
afar that he still thinks that that
could happen I mean if we saw what
happened to Julian Assange just a couple
weeks back when they had 15 minutes of
prepares defense he said the word not
guilty that was it
and the judge ranted about what a
narcissist he was I'm like well is this
the kind of kangaroo court that Ed
Snowden can expect to get into I think
so in this culture in this climate right
precisely
the deck is stacked and you know and I'm
not to heap on but I'm gonna heap on
these
we've all been charged in the Eastern
District of Virginia I was charged there
Snowden was charged there his charges of
course are still pending Julian's been
charged there Jeffrey sterling the CIA
whistle blowers charged there and judge
Leonie brinkema reserves all national
security cases for herself and so what
what did she do before she before
President Reagan appointed her to the
federal bench she was a prosecutor in
the Eastern District of Virginia and
under her judgeship no national security
defendant has ever won a case never when
when I was sentenced my attorneys
negotiated something called an 11 C 1 C
plea very very unusual plea and what it
means is the defendant has agreed to
plead guilty in exchange for a sentence
that the two sides negotiated the
sentence is written in stone and it
cannot be altered by the judge and she
said to me at sentencing that this was
the first 11 C 1 C plea that she had
ever had and she's been a judge since
1986 and she said to me mr. kuryakin I
don't like it I don't like it one bit if
I could I would send you to prison for
the next ten years and that told me that
the whole case the whole trial and
everything that we had we had worked on
was just it was window dressing because
she had made up her mind in the very
beginning I was guilty because everybody
is guilty and I was going to prison it
was just a question of how long right
she and that's the thing to use like
we're when I hear when I hear stuff like
this what what angers me is the autonomy
we like like the other day some judge
went to jail for for trafficking
literally trafficking black teens into
private prisons right yeah he got 20
years you got disbarred yes you're right
that that should not be so unusual that
it makes the news that should be so
commonplace like I'm from LA I grew up
in South Central
so
you know when you hear about drive-by
shootings never made the news
you know I they happen all the time we
should hear about spoiled rotten DA's
and corrupt judges getting busted right
going to jail all the time it shouldn't
be so rare right you're right you're
absolutely right and but so so quickly
because you know I definitely maximize
our time together I want to get back to
a little bit you were recruited in 1990
so we're about the same age that you're
just you're just what out of grad school
yeah I had just gotten out of grad
school actually was one of my grad
school professors who was well he was
undercover as a professor he was
actually a CIA spotter looking for
people who would fit into the CIA
culture he recruited me in grad school
that was my okay that was my question
that and he wanted me to ominous about
it cuz they're one of the greatest films
on the OSS CIA transition ever made was
a movie called The Good Shepherd with
Matt Damon yeah based on the novel yeah
and actually I own it I must've seen it
50 times and brother my brother got me
into it and anyway went you know when I
saw it when I saw in your background
like 90 I wonder if they got it I wonder
if they got you the same way they got
Matt Damon's character right so yeah you
know and that's that's actually illegal
now with passage of the Equal Employment
Opportunity Act in 1993 they can't do
that anymore but that's why it was such
an old boy kind of kind of agency
because what they did is they they took
these senior officers or even retired
senior officers they cast them all
around the country to universities and
and they just kind of sat quietly
pretended to be professors they would
teach a class here and there and then
they would pick and choose who they like
to they thought would be a good fit how
did you fit into that culture because I
know you come from a Greek background I
mean I only asked as my dad's era but my
mother's Brazilian I'm happy I'm
first-generation American and and that
you know I've had some stuff thrown at
me especially by like you know waspy
types right yeah and you being Greek
it's like yeah I mean yeah yeah in the
Northeast yeah
because the place was still it was still
a waspey white man's paradise over there
when I first joined it wasn't until Bill
Clinton became president that they that
they actively began to to recruit it
try to attract talented minorities and
women I mean there was even a
class-action suit get this as late as
1994 I had already been in the agency
five years and there was a class-action
suit by all female CIA employees saying
that they had been passed over for
promotion just because they were women
and in the in a decision
the federal judge also in the Eastern
District of Virginia said that he had
never seen a case where the defendant
had so clearly documented his own crime
as the CIA had done and so what they did
is they issued an across-the-board
two-level promotion for every woman in
the entire CIA Wow yeah that's pretty
bad huh yeah that's a lot of that's a
lot of people a lot of people it's a lot
of brood over the years yeah a hundred
percent well and then at what at what
point did you because none of these
things well some of these things I
suppose are epiphanies but at what point
did you was it a development did she had
a that was the crisis of conscious
developer did one day you just had this
epiphany you're going what the [__] are
we doing with these people you know what
it was all post 9/11 until 9/11 I really
did believe that we were the good guys
and I believed that you know when you
would read about this about this stuff
these you know we human rights
violations and such that they were that
they were anomalies they were exception
in in the 1990s when Bill Clinton was
president the CIA underwent something
called a call see you ll where they went
through the files of literally every
recruited asset in the world and if any
asset had any history in his file of
human rights abuses he was fired and
they just got him off they fired fully
one-third of their recruited agents
around the world and I thought wow Bill
Clinton is serious about human rights
man this is going to be a new day for us
and it was until September 11th and then
it was like flipping a switch they went
back to the bad old days of before the
the Church Committee and the pike
committee and they just started
killing everybody next thing you know
there's a torture program there's a
directed assassination program there's
an extraordinary rendition program
there's a system of secret prisons
popping up all over the world that
nobody knows about it was like like I
said it was like flipping a switch Wow
yeah and then Wow and so so literally
the switch flipped for you and you saw
this happened you are in your agents in
September limits made me as angry as it
made anybody else in America right I
wanted I volunteered three times before
they sent me out as the chief of
counterterrorism in Pakistan mmm I was
ready to do literally anything that
needed to be done to help to protect the
country
but then little by little I started
seeing these things and I'm like wow
wait a minute I've given one small
example the night that we captured up as
a beta hmm we also captured a lot of
other al-qaeda fighters I'm not allowed
to say the number but it was many dozens
of al-qaeda fighters and we had we had
caught so many of them we had to bring
them into the safe house in in shifts to
interrogate them and one of my
colleagues brought a paddy wagon full of
about a dozen and they were all wearing
hoods and I said why are these guys
wearing hoods and he said well they're
al Qaeda we don't want him to see our
identities and I said have you seriously
never read the Geneva Convention is that
what you're telling me or you've never
read the Geneva Convention you cannot
put hoods on them mmm take those hoods
off right now the guy says I'm gonna
report you to headquarters I said Oh
believe me I'm reporting you to General
Council because you just committed a war
crime Wow take those effort hoods off
Wow yeah and it was that night which
should have been the greatest night of
my career it was that night that I
started thinking I think we may have
fallen off the edge here right and
that's just one small example did that
make you sort of retrace our steps
though because I mean about you know
because literally at when we went into
Iraq and you know I was one of the few
people this is a bad idea
like you know was a dick
yeah how many dictators are in the world
we can't go pop in the you know the cork
off of every shitty bottle of wine and
then deal with the Sal
leave it alone that's right not our
business let our problem let the people
handle it and he had nothing to do with
[__] 9/11 and so you know the long the
long and the short of it is it made me
kind of retrace all of our misdeeds I
mean you know the main talking yeah you
know the Korean War you know Pentagon
you know you can't talk about Panama
without talking about to Rios and see
you go or treat us rather so you go you
go back so now I'm all the way back to
the Civil War I'm like well [__] was
that even real I mean you know the folks
the Fort Sumter thing might have been a
total hoax just to get us into that war
as Lincoln had to get us into that war
yeah it right did it make you did this
start to make you kind of retrace your
steps as where are steps I actually I
actually go over this in great detail in
my first book I got back from Pakistan
and on the strength of the Abu Zubaydah
capture I get promoted and I'm named
deputy director to the I'm sorry
executive assistant to the deputy
director so on my first day of work I go
into the office and I say to him okay
what are we gonna do and he said
actually I can't tell you until you go
up to the sixth floor and you have to
sign a whole bunch of secrecy agreements
so I go up there and knock on the door
and I go in and it got all these secrecy
agreements laid out on a desk and and
and I said I'm here to sign them and he
gives me a pen and I sign all six of
these things and when I finished I said
okay so what gives and he says well next
year in February we are going to invade
Iraq we're going to overthrow Saddam
Hussein we are going to install our own
puppet we're going to open the world's
largest Air Force Base in southern Iraq
and we're going to move all of our air
assets out of Saudi Arabia into Iraq to
deprive Osama bin Laden of the ability
to say that we are polluting the land of
the Two Holy Mosques and I was so
dumbfounded I just stared at him and
finally I said but we haven't caught bin
Laden yet and he said buddy
he said the decisions already been made
and here's how it lines up he said on
the one side you've got the office of
the vice president the office of the
Secretary of Defense and the National
Security Council on the other side you
have the CIA the State Department and
the Joint Chiefs of Staff and guess
which side loses and that was it
nobody at the CIA wanted to go into Iraq
we wanted to kill every last al-qaeda
fighter on the face of the planet and we
had to hunt down bin Laden but Dick
Cheney said no no we don't care about
bin Laden anymore we're gonna go into
Iraq and we're gonna overthrow Saddam
Hussein and we're going to take
everything those people have dammit yep
see and that's what makes me something
oh you too Wyndham I went into an office
in something called the Iraq Operations
Group one day I went up to to pick up a
briefing book and and the guy who had
given me the the secrecy agreements to
sign he was the director of Iraq
operations so these are you know serious
these are high-level people I'm dealing
with every day
and he's sitting there at his desk and
he's got these Crayola colored markers
and he's coloring something so I said
what are you doing and he said oh I'm
designing the new Iraqi flag and I said
don't you think maybe the Iraqis should
design the new Iraqi flag and he looks
at me and he says not necessarily and I
thought man we are in serious trouble
here serious trouble
this gets right back to the sykes-picot
thing it's it it's at white absolutely
it's too white imperialists on a bar
napkin in in in the world yeah they're
like okay well when when the Turks go
down this is how it's gonna go down
and and you know the first Shah was
appointed that's why I when when the
first Shah ran afoul of the Brits and
the Russians with with what a
nationalized Iranian oil in the 20s they
were like well [__] that and they
removed him and installed the the second
Shah who we know to be the Shah and and
you know that whole story so I mean my
point in all my point in all that is is
we just don't seem to learn our last
lessons from this colonial white
imperialism and that's all it is you
know like I mean all it is my dad's
Palestinian right so I've heard all
kinds of crap my whole life
one thing that amazed me I remember in
the 90s you know when everyone was about
saving the Muslims I'm like yeah you
really care what their why don't you cuz
you know when they're brown Muslims you
don't seem to give a [__] I mean it's
just it's just sort of that way and what
you're what you're describing right now
it's pretty much the sykes-picot thing
yeah that's exactly what it is you know
when when the Brits finally you know
came to the realization that they
weren't the global power they had once
been we said oh no problem we can take
it from here and that's exactly what
happened yeah that's exactly and we
became the reserve currency and that's
why we can afford to do these stupid
regime change wars because we keep
printing the money to do it but you know
a few years back we almost got voted out
of being reserve currency
but I think we I think we barely stayed
in by two votes so you know Trump
committing his [__] all around the
world pissing people off I don't know
how the votes gonna go next time if they
make the the Petru on their reserve
currency we could be in for a lot of
problems is that's something that I'm
far-fetched on thinking but I think
you're right well it's really it's
really it's really too bad that I'm
right because I'm just a guy with a day
job
as a Mike and that's it I don't have any
I don't have any credentials I don't I
didn't go to like journalism school or
anything like that listen John I know um
your times a little tight I know you
host your podcast loud and clear is
there anything else that you wanted it
and I know you have a your website John
Kerry aku com
is there any else did you want to share
with share with the listeners oh thank
you no that's about it John Kiriakou
comm I'm on Twitter and Facebook and all
the usual stuff
excellent excellent well what I'll do is
I'll put you know I'll definitely put
links to your stuff in the you know body
of the of the show but again I'd loved
I'd love to have you come on again as
some of the some later point and as
things develop I was gonna ask you about
Daniel Hale but we're out of time but my
pleasure but I'm happy to talk to you
about Dan you know the next time
absolutely
well hey listen folks um my guest has
been John Kerry aku noted
author host of loud and clear again you
could become a bitter pill by visiting
patreon.com for just less the bitter
truth and if this stuff makes you
uncomfortable its supposed to sleep
tight
[Applause]
[Music]